Hello everyone and welcome back to EnglishPod.
大家好，欢迎回到EnglishPod。
My name is Marco.
我是Marco。
And my name is Catherine.
我是Catherine。
And it's the holiday season so that means more Christmas songs for you guys.
现在是假期季节，所以这意味着你们会听到更多圣诞歌曲。
That's right.
没错。
And today we're going to be taking a look at a very famous song, very relaxed but very
今天我们要来看一首非常著名的歌曲，非常舒缓但又非常
beautiful song called Silent Night.
美丽的歌曲，叫《平安夜》。
Yeah, this is one of those songs that you hear everywhere but unlike Jingle Bells which
是的，这是一首你到处都能听到的歌，但不像《铃儿响叮当》那样
is like jingle bells, jingle bells, not, you know, very cheery and uplifting and shopping
是“叮叮当，叮叮当”，你知道的，非常欢快、振奋人心，适合购物时播放的
music.
音乐。
This is more, as Marco said, calm, peaceful, almost church music.
这首歌更像Marco说的那样，平静、祥和，几乎是教堂音乐。
So we're going to find out what the words mean in this very classic song.
所以我们要来了解这首经典歌曲的歌词含义。
Right, it's classic and very religious because it has a connotation towards the Catholic
对，它很经典，而且带有宗教色彩，因为它与天主教
religion.
有关联。
So why don't we listen to the song and then we'll be back to explain it.
那我们不如先听一下这首歌，然后再回来解释。
Silent night, holy night, all is calm, all is bright.
平安夜，圣善夜，万暗中，光华射。
Round yon virgin, mother and child, holy infant so tender and mild.
照着圣母也照着圣婴，多少慈祥也多少天真。
Sleep in heavenly peace.
静享天赐安眠。
Alright we're back.
好了，我们回来了。
So now let's take a look at this song line by line.
现在让我们逐行来看这首歌的歌词。
So we're not going to do the standard format of picking out words.
我们不会用标准的挑单词格式。
We're going to do it line by line to kind of get a good feel for this dialogue.
我们会逐行分析，以便更好地感受这段对话。
So first of all some background.
首先，介绍一下背景。
Okay so the 24th, the evening, Mary and Joseph are looking for a place to stay.
好的，24号晚上，玛丽和约瑟夫在找地方住。
Mary, the virgin mother of God, is going to give birth to a baby.
玛丽，上帝之母，童贞女，即将生下婴儿。
And they need a place to stay so finally they find a place.
他们需要找个地方住，最后终于找到了一个地方。
It's not a hotel, it's not a house.
不是酒店，也不是房子。
It's like an inn.
是个客栈。
Yeah, well it's actually the stables for the inn, right?
对，实际上是客栈的马厩，对吧？
Yeah, the stables for the inn, yeah.
是的，客栈的马厩。
And so what the song is celebrating is what happens afterwards, after the baby Jesus is
所以这首歌庆祝的是之后发生的事情，在婴儿耶稣
born.
出生之后。
So that's where we are.
这就是我们的背景。
Alright, so the first line says silent night, holy night.
好的，第一行是“平安夜，圣善夜”。
As you know it's holy, that means it's religiously special, it's important.
你知道，“圣善”意味着它在宗教上是特别的、重要的。
Okay, all is calm, all is bright.
好的，“万暗中，光华射”。
So we talk about bright light sometimes.
我们有时会谈论明亮的光。
Something is bright if it gives a lot of light off.
如果某物发出很多光，它就是明亮的。
And well the next line is very interesting because it says round yon virgin mother and
下一行非常有趣，因为它说“照着圣母也照着圣婴”。
child.
Now you see this first two words there, round yon.
现在你看到前两个词“照着”。
What is round yon?
“照着”是什么意思？
So round comes from around.
“照着”来自“照耀”。
Yon means over there.
“也”意思是“也”。
So around over there, so over there we've got two people.
所以“照着……也照着”，意思是那边有两个人。
Over there we've got the virgin mother and her child.
那边有圣母和她的孩子。
Okay so the virgin mother is Mary, right?
好的，所以圣母就是玛丽，对吧？
That's right.
没错。
And the child would be Jesus.
孩子就是耶稣。
Exactly.
正是。
And it says holy infant, so tender and mild.
歌词说“多少慈祥也多少天真”。
Okay so what is an infant?
好的，“婴儿”是什么？
An infant is a baby, some baby that's just been born.
“婴儿”就是刚出生的宝宝。
So we can say that infants are very, very delicate.
所以我们可以说婴儿非常非常娇嫩。
You have to be very careful when you hold an infant.
抱婴儿的时候要非常小心。
But in this case a holy infant is Jesus, he's special for religious reasons.
但在这里，“圣婴”指的是耶稣，他因宗教原因而特殊。
And when they say that he's tender and mild, what does he mean by that?
当歌词说他“慈祥”和“天真”时，是什么意思？
Well you talk about tender things when you're talking about things that are soft, delicate,
嗯，当你谈论柔软、娇嫩、
gentle or sweet.
温柔或甜美的事物时，你会用“慈祥”。
And something that is mild or someone that is mild is very quiet and calm and gentle.
而“天真”或某人“天真”意味着非常安静、平静和温柔。
So not making much noise.
所以不会发出太多噪音。
So the baby is very sweet, very tender and wasn't crying or making a big fuss.
所以这个婴儿非常可爱、非常温柔，没有哭闹或大惊小怪。
And then we have sleep in heavenly peace, sleep in heavenly peace.
然后我们听到“静享天赐安眠”。
Well the baby's quiet because the baby's sleeping.
婴儿很安静，因为婴儿在睡觉。
So you're saying sleep in heavenly peace, that means may the peace of heaven, because
所以你说“静享天赐安眠”，意思是愿天堂的平安，
heaven is a very peaceful place, the most peaceful place, may that peace be with you
因为天堂是一个非常和平的地方，最和平的地方，愿那份平安与你同在
when you're sleeping.
当你睡觉的时候。
Okay, very good.
好的，非常好。
And moving on we have silent night, holy night again.
继续，我们又听到“平安夜，圣善夜”。
But then they say shepherds quake at the sight.
但接着他们说“牧羊人，在旷野”。
So what is this?
这是什么意思？
Shepherds we know that these are people that take care of sheep.
“牧羊人”我们知道是照顾羊的人。
That's right, they make the sheep move from one place to another.
没错，他们让羊群从一个地方移动到另一个地方。
And it says they quake at the sight.
歌词说他们“在旷野”。
So they quake at the sight of what?
他们在旷野看到了什么？
Well quake, we often say quiver in one's boots.
嗯，“在旷野”，我们常说“在野外”。
So to quake means to shake when you're nervous.
所以“在旷野”意思是当你在野外时感到颤抖。
So you know when you're going to make a speech in front of many, many, many people, your
你知道，当你要在很多人面前演讲时，你的
hands start to shake, that's called quaking.
手开始颤抖，这就叫“颤抖”。
So to quake.
所以是“颤抖”。
So shepherds quake, they're nervous at the sight, well the sight is the noun for seeing
所以牧羊人在旷野，他们看到景象时很紧张，景象是看到
something.
某物的名词。
The sight of Jesus.
看到耶稣的景象。
Of the baby.
看到婴儿的景象。
Okay, okay, okay, okay.
好的，好的，好的，好的。
Glories stream from heaven afar.
“荣光从天而降”。
So glories stream from heaven afar.
所以“荣光从天而降”。
Okay, the verb here, the action word is to stream.
好的，这里的动词是“降”。
To stream.
“降”。
Okay, that means to come down.
好的，意思是流下来。
Okay.
好的。
Okay, so to come down in kind of big amounts.
好的，所以是大量地流下来。
So we have glory, glory, so happiness and joy and glory and good things coming down
所以我们有“荣光”，荣光，所以幸福、喜悦、荣耀和美好的事物从天而降
from the heavens.
从天上。
So lots of positive, good things coming down from heaven.
所以很多积极、美好的事物从天而降。
And where is heaven?
天在哪里？
Afar.
远方。
So the key part of this is the word far.
所以关键部分是“远”这个词。
It's far away, right?
它是遥远的，对吧？
Yeah.
是的。
Afar is an old word we use to describe something that's far away.
“远方”是一个古老的词，我们用来描述遥远的事物。
So the heavens afar, the heavens that are far away are giving us all of this joy and
所以“远方的天”，遥远的天堂给了我们所有这些喜悦和
happiness.
幸福。
Okay.
好的。
And then the song says heavenly hosts sing hallelujah.
然后歌词说“天军齐声唱哈利路亚”。
So heavenly hosts, those are bodies or people or spirits in the sky.
所以“天军”是天空中的群体、人或灵体。
Like angels.
比如天使。
Angels.
天使。
They're singing hallelujah.
他们在唱“哈利路亚”。
So hallelujah is a word that we often use in the Christian religion that comes from
所以“哈利路亚”是我们在基督教中经常使用的一个词，实际上来自
Greek actually.
希腊语。
Oh really?
哦，真的吗？
Yeah.
是的。
So hallelujah is a Greek word and it means celebrate, joy, amen.
所以“哈利路亚”是一个希腊词，意思是庆祝、喜悦、阿门。
Okay, hallelujah.
好的，哈利路亚。
It's something you're happy about.
这是你感到高兴的事情。
Hallelujah.
哈利路亚。
And then they say Christ, the savior is born.
然后他们说“基督，救世主诞生了”。
Now we have this, the savior.
现在我们有了这个，救世主。
What is it?
这是什么？
Who is a savior?
谁是救世主？
What is a savior?
什么是救世主？
It's a very good question.
这是个很好的问题。
A savior is a word we only really, well, we don't hear that often, but you've heard the
“救世主”这个词我们其实不常听到，但你肯定听过
word to save before.
“拯救”这个词。
So for example, I fell into the water and Marco jumped in and saved me.
比如，我掉进水里，Marco跳进来救了我。
So I would be a savior?
那我就是救世主吗？
Marco is my savior.
Marco是我的救世主。
He saved me.
他救了我。
But in this case, savior refers to the Bible and the things that Jesus did later.
但在这里，救世主指的是圣经和耶稣所做的事。
So we say in Christianity, he saved people, the humankind.
所以在基督教中，我们说耶稣拯救了人类。
So he is the savior.
所以他是救世主。
Christ the savior.
基督救世主。
All right.
好的。
And then our next verse, it says, silent night, holy night, son of God loves pure light, radiant
然后下一句歌词是：平安夜，圣善夜，神子爱，纯洁光，光芒四射从你圣容。
beams from thy holy face.
光芒四射从你圣容。
So we have radiant beams and then we have this word thy.
所以我们有“光芒四射”和“你的”这个词。
So these beams is like a beam of light, right?
这些“光芒”就像一束光，对吧？
It's like a line of light, but you know how light is clear.
就像一条光线，但你知道光是清澈的。
So a beam of light is something that comes down in a straight line.
所以一束光就是直线射下来的东西。
You can see it.
你能看到它。
So for example, when I turn on a flashlight and there's a line of light, that's a beam.
比如，我打开手电筒，有一条光线，那就是一束光。
And radiant means it's very bright.
“光芒四射”意思是它非常明亮。
It's very clear.
非常清澈。
Clear and it's strong and it's coming out from that one place.
清澈、强烈，从那个地方射出来。
And what about this word thy?
那“你的”这个词呢？
It's very popular, like old English, right?
这很常见，像古英语，对吧？
It's an old English form of saying you.
这是古英语中“你”的一种形式。
So in the olden days in English, we had different ways of saying the word you.
所以在古英语中，我们有不同的方式说“你”。
And so thy is one of those words and you hear this very often.
“你的”就是其中之一，你经常听到。
And so in this sentence, we're saying radiant beams from thy holy face.
所以在这句话中，我们说“光芒四射从你圣容”。
We're now starting to talk to Jesus because we're referring to him.
我们现在开始对耶稣说话，因为我们在指代他。
You radiant beams, light is coming out of your face.
你光芒四射，光从你的脸上射出来。
Your holy face.
你的圣容。
Because you're such a holy.
因为你是如此神圣。
I think you can probably see this thy and thou in Shakespeare, for example, right?
我想你可能在莎士比亚的作品中看到过“你的”和“汝”，对吧？
Exactly.
没错。
Shakespeare, the Bible, prayers, and all sorts of old books and poetry.
莎士比亚、圣经、祈祷文，以及各种古书和诗歌中都有。
And then we say with the dawn of redeeming grace.
然后我们说“随着救赎恩典的黎明”。
So what is to redeem?
那么什么是“救赎”？
To redeem is to find value in something that didn't have value before.
“救赎”就是在一件原本没有价值的东西中找到价值。
So maybe I have a ticket for some, okay, I won a small lottery ticket, $5.
比如我有一张彩票，好吧，我中了五美元的小奖。
I go to the store to redeem my money.
我去商店兑换我的钱。
The paper is worthless, but it's worth something when I redeem it.
那张纸一文不值，但当我兑换时它就有价值了。
So Christ the Redeemer, when he saves people, he redeems them.
所以基督救赎主，当他拯救人们时，他救赎了他们。
He gives them value again.
他重新赋予他们价值。
Very good.
非常好。
So it's a very profound song, right?
所以这是一首非常深刻的歌，对吧？
And it talks about, as we say, about Jesus, about angels, and it's very, very religious.
它讲的是，如我们所说，关于耶稣、天使，非常非常宗教化。
So it's a great song and it's, well, it's a very popular song.
所以这是一首很棒的歌，而且，嗯，是一首非常流行的歌。
And well, even if you don't share the religious connotation that the song has, it still is
而且，即使你不认同这首歌的宗教含义，它仍然
very popular in North America and many parts of the world.
在北美和世界许多地方非常流行。
So why don't we have a listen to this song one last time?
那我们最后再听一遍这首歌吧？
So when I was a little girl at school, we had to sing this in German.
我小时候在学校，我们得用德语唱这首歌。
So I know that there are some other countries that have the same song with different words.
所以我知道有些其他国家有同样的歌，但歌词不同。
So it's the same rhythm and everything, but just in German.
节奏和一切都一样，只是用德语唱。
And is it pretty much the same idea, the same words?
意思和歌词差不多吗？
Yeah, almost exactly the same, just in a translated form.
是的，几乎完全一样，只是翻译版。
Maybe it came from German, I don't know.
也许它来自德语，我不知道。
Because it seems to be pretty old, right?
因为它看起来挺古老的，对吧？
But it is a very common song during Christmas.
但这是一首在圣诞节非常常见的歌。
And even many times, Christmas carolers will go around in the neighborhood and sing these
而且很多时候，圣诞颂歌者会在社区里四处走动，在不同地方唱这些
songs in different places, right?
歌，对吧？
Exactly.
没错。
And it's a really beautiful song, one of my favorites.
而且这是一首非常美的歌，是我最喜欢的之一。
And I'm not a religious person, so I don't really like it for the religious perspective
我不是一个宗教人士，所以我不太喜欢它从宗教角度
that it gives.
传达的东西。
But I do think that it's just one of those beautiful classic songs that makes the season
但我确实认为它只是那些美丽的经典歌曲之一，让这个季节
very warm and special.
变得非常温暖和特别。
The music is nice in this song.
这首歌的音乐很好听。
Alright, so an interesting song and I'm sure we're going to have a lot of questions and
好了，一首有趣的歌，我相信我们会有很多问题和
comments about it.
评论。
So we expect to see you guys on our website EnglishPod.com and we'll see you guys there.
所以我们期待在我们的网站EnglishPod.com上见到你们，我们会在那里见。
Happy holidays and enjoy.
节日快乐，享受吧。
Bye guys.
再见，各位。
Enjoy Christmas, sing along with us.
享受圣诞节，和我们一起唱吧。